Shantnu Gupta

• +1(470)424-0543 • sgupta38@student.gsu.edu • https://www.linkedin.com/in/shantnu-gupta-gp/ • https://github.com/BrownBatman

Motivated, teamwork-oriented data analyst with significant experience of 3+ years in solving complex business problems using SQL, Python, and MS Excel for fast-paced product and services teams. Seeking full-time and summer internship opportunities in Data Science and analytics.

COMPETENCIES

- Programming SQL, Python, R, Java, SAS Databases MySQL, T-SQL, BigQuery, DataBricks, Teradata, Oracle, SQLite
- Skills Machine Learning, K Means Clustering, Bayesian Inference, Hypothesis Testing, NLP, Web-Crawling, A/B Testing, Data Mining, ETL, Deep Learning, A/B Testing, Anova, Classification
- Libraries pandas, scikit-learn, matplotlib, NumPy, seaborn, TensorFlow, pyspark, NLTK Platforms Hadoop, Spark, Linux, Microsoft Azure, AWS
- Tools Visual Studio Code, SQL Server, Power BI, Microsoft Office Suite, Stata, Jupyter Notebook, MS Excel, Tableau, MS PowerPoint

EDUCATION

J. Mack Robinson College of Business, Georgia State University, Atlanta

Master of Science in Data Science and Analytics

(August 2021 - April 2023)

Master of Science in Quantitative Risk Analysis and Management

(August 2021 - April 2023)

1. Web Scraped data of Fortune 500 for better Earnings Per Share Estimations

- o Scraped the data using selenium(python) and created a database from scraped data with non-redundant and normalized tables for better query execution time.
- o Executed multiple regression algorithms(Linear and Logistic) to predict the Earning per Share for fortune 500 companies.

2. Movie/Sitcoms Recommendation System

- o Performed exploratory data analysis and data cleaning on Netflix and IMDB data to draw meaningful patterns and insights.
- Built the enhanced recommendation model on Netflix data applying K-Nearest Neighbour manually to predict the top 10 most similar movies/sitcoms.

Bundelkhand Institute of Engineering and Technology, Jhansi, Up

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering

(August 2013 - June 2017)

1. Email Spam Classifier

- Cleaned the data(Enron Emails) using **NLTK** library to help remove poor quality results from our machine learning model.
- Designed a spam classifier model to predict whether the email is spam or not using a Naïve Bayesian algorithm with an accuracy of 93%.

2. Monte Carlo Simulations on Betting

- Build a simulator to help one visualize most or all of the potential outcomes involved in betting decision-making.
- Through the simulations of randomized betting trials, we concluded that "House Always Wins" even with a 49% probability of winning.

EXPERIENCE

Georgia State University

(Atlanta, Georgia, USA)

(January 2022- Current) **Graduate Research Assistant**

Working in a mutual fund lab, to mine insights between mutual fund disclosures and inflation using Text Analytics(topic modeling)

Starr Insurance Graduate Research Assistant

(Atlanta, Georgia, USA) (August 2021 - December 2021)

Developed a model to predict the likelihood of an existing customer if they will buy the recommended add-ons insurance using basic statistics and Random Forest Classifier.

Bipp Consulting

(Agra, Uttar Pradesh, India) (September 2020 - July 2021)

Business Intelligence Analyst

- Streamlined, backtracked, and automated 4 KPI's for Johnson & Johnson, which reduced the person-hours by 30%.
- Decreased database complexity by normalizing and optimizing tables and queries in Johnson & Johnson SQL Databases, reducing production time by approximately 20%.

ParallelDots

(Gurgaon, Harvana, India)

Senior Business Analyst

(July 2019 - August 2020)

- Created processes and solutions for seamless execution of multiple projects, which involved image processing of 3 million images per month in helping Hindustan Unilever identify critical aspects of advertising, thereby increasing sales by 3%-4%.
- Fostered resources of 27 data annotation employees and multiple business analysts according to skill, timeline, relevance, and revenue.
- Performed sentiment analysis using logistic regression on survey results for Indian tobacco company that helped them launch 2 low-cost products in the Indian market, increasing their market share by 2%.

Decision Point Analytics

(Gurgaon, Haryana, India) (December 2018 - June 2019)

Business Analyst

Collected, cleansed, and transformed 10TB of structured and unstructured Coke Data on Big Query every month.

- Created PowerBI reports based on sales to identify key marketing strategies for Coke in Latam Region.
- Drove the improvements in database processes resulting in a decrease in time and daily data usage in Big Query, which reduces the overall server cost by 25% and data processing time by 10%.

MAQ Software

(Hyderabad, Telangana, India) (March 2018 - December 2018)

Software Engineer

- Developed a workflow in SSIS to improvise user experience by streamlining incoming survey data from Adobe Omniture for Microsoft.
- Created interactive dashboards using PowerBI to analyze the hit ratio of web pages, thus identifying pages with more traffic.
- Implemented funnel analytics and statistics on web traffic data of Microsoft which led to 10% increase in user signups.

CERTIFICATES AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 761-QUERYING DATA WITH TRANSACT-SQL by Microsoft.
- 778-ANALYZING AND VISUALIZING DATA WITH MICROSOFT POWER BI by Microsoft.
- MICROSOFT CERTIFIED PROFESSIONAL: MICROSOFT CERTIFIED PROFESSIONAL by Microsoft.
- RANK 1 and GOLDEN BADGE in SQL MODULE on HACKERANK. (USERNAME- BrownBatman)